Just now we were dealing with
liveness notions, i.e. properties of Petri
nets that have something to
do with liveness (in various degrees).
And this was about the structure of
the Petri net or the corresponding reachability graph.
Not about the numbers
that were in there.
So it was not about the
number of tokens on single positions.
But it was about whether
certain transitions are executable, again
and again or
at least once.
Whether a node can
be a dead end.
So in the end it was
about the structure of the graphs,
not about the content of
the single places in a marking.
So it
wasn't about numbers.
That's
changing now.
It's now about properties that have
something to do exactly with those numbers.
That corresponds to the
informal questions from earlier
in the lecture, about bounds
or capacities of individual places.
So do we want that
there can never be more than
so-and-so many tokens in
one place, for example?
This would be expressed in the
reachability graph by the fact that in
the tuples that
we write into the
nodes, for example, the individual entries
can never exceed a certain number.
This is about
the concept of "boundedness".
And there is first of all a
term, which is called "safe" or "1-safe".
And it's first defined
here on the slide.
So a Petri net is
1-safe if the following holds:
First, for every transition t and every place
s that the Petri net has, this expression, the
preweight function of t applied to
s, is less than or equal
to 1 (that is,
zero or one; negative is
not possible anyway, here we
only assume natural numbers including zero).
So if it says "less than or equal to
1", it can only mean: either zero or one.
Either there is no transition at all,
no arrow in the Petri net from this
place to this transition (and then
from there perhaps into other places).
Or, if there is a connection there,
it is one without an extra weight,
just a simple
arrow with weight 1.
And the same is
true for the post weights.
So for any t
and any s, the
post-weight function of t applied to s also
has the value at most 0 or 1.
So all weights
at most 1.
This is first a structural
property of the Petri net.
I can look at the
Petri net and ultimately see:
Is there something else, something greater than
a 1 attached to a weight somewhere?
In addition, a
dynamic property also applies.
Namely, even in the reachability graph,
it must be the case that every
reachable marking (i.e., the m0 itself, but
also every marking that can be reached from
there) also has the property that for
every location that the Petri net has,
the marking for that location gives
a value of 1 at most.
That is, if we have the tuple
notation of our nodes (of the markings
in the nodes), then there must never be
a component there that is not 0 or 1.
Thus we can already say
quite clearly, as simple example, that
for example this Petri
net is not 1-safe.
We can see this immediately, because it
has for example a 2 here, and also
because the start tokener has more than
one token on at least one place.
So already here you would see that
to the Petri net in this representation.
Of course, we could also
look at the reachability graph.
And there we see immediately, especially already
in the start marking (but also in
other markings) in any
case numbers greater than 1.
So this is quite blatantly
not 1-safe, for various reasons.
Both concerning this fact, that this
2 is here for example, and
because of observations
about the reachability graph.
If a Petri net may be called "1-safe",
it must have both the property that there
is never a number greater than 1 as
a weight in the Petri net representation, and
that every reachable marking
(i.e. every node in
the reachability graph) must not
contain anything greater than 1.
This is indeed
a very strong restriction.
Of course, "reachable" here means
"reachable from the start marking".
Now I have discussed an
example that is blatantly not 1-safe.
Are there also Petri nets that
we have already discussed that are 1-safe?
Yes. Those were
all 1-safe Petri nets.
Here, there are never any weights
greater than 1 in the representations
of the Petri nets themselves, and if
you look at the reachability graphs for these
Petri nets again in the previous video, you will
never find a component greater than 1 there either.
Therefore, these have actually all
been examples of 1-safe Petri nets.
This check that there
is never anything greater than
1 in the reachability graph is, of course,
only feasible if the reachability graph is finite.
But it will be
if this property holds.
So this refers
to "1-safe": weights
only 1, each marking contains only
at most one token per place, etc.
This is
very bounded.
In fact "1-safe" or "1-bounded",
but you say "1-safe" to it.
Besides that, there are other notions
of boundedness, which also allow larger value.
Which in particular do not already restrict
the weights in the Petri net itself.
But they only restrict
that the markings in
the reachability graph must
be bounded by a constant.
And this does not necessarily
have to be the constant 1.
So a
Petri net is
called "bounded" if there is
some constant, some natural number.
This can be 1, of course,
but it can also be 15.
And what
should be valid?
For this constant it should be valid
that every reachable marking m, i.e. every
marking reachable from m0, has the property that for every place
s (i.e. in every component in tuple notation) there is a
number which is at most c. If c
= 15, then this number should not be c.
If c = 15, there
should be no number greater than
15 anywhere in
the reachability graph.
If there are only numbers up to
15, then the Petri net would be bounded.
And what weights are in the Petri
net itself does not matter at all.
So here
only the reachability
graph is referred to
and the reachable markings.
And that can be
determined in the reachability graph.
And for this there
is the opposite, namely "unbounded".
A Petri net is unbounded
if this is just not true.
But if for each constant c there is a
marking m reachable from m0 and a place (not
all places, but one place), so that actually
times a value larger than c is assumed.
So "bounded" and "unbounded" are actually
the exact opposite of each other.
While "1-safe" is not
somehow opposite of either property.
How could
one test this?
How could one
test these properties?
Well, first of all, of course, it is
true that every 1-safe Petri net is also bounded.
One could test
for boundedness first.
And then, if
it is bounded, look:
Is it
even 1-safe?
If a Petri net is
unbounded, it is certainly not 1-safe.
Because the fact that here
values greater than c are assumed,
contradicts of course
the "maximum 1".
And this distinction "bounded/unbounded" can
be determined by the reachability graph.
Namely, a Petri net is unbounded
exactly when the reachability graph is infinite.
Or
formulated differently:
A Petri net is bounded if and
only if the reachability graph is finite.
That is, while our example here
was not 1-safe, it is definitely bounded.
We can't see
that here yet.
The Petri net itself is
not so relevant to boundedness/unboundedness.
But the reachability graph,
and that is finite.
We even see here what
the smallest constant c is.
For the constant c = 3, it is true here that
there is never a node that has an entry greater than 3.
Of course, that would be true
here for c = 15 as well.
But 3 is
the interesting constant here.
Namely, it is the smallest
one that can be chosen.
For c = 2
this would not be true.
Then there is indeed a marking
containing a value greater than 2.
And the
graph is finite.
It could become infinite only if
there are also arbitrarily large entries.
That is, if there
is no such bounding constant.
Any Petri net
with finite reachability graph
will have such a maximum constant
and then it is also bounded.
Any Petri net
that is not bounded
will automatically have
an infinite reachability graph.
And of course, we can then
check 1-safety by doing syntactic checking on
the
one hand.
So just looking
at the Petri net
itself, and if that's already not satisfied,
then the Petri net is not 1-safe either.
If the
first property is
satisfied, that no numbers greater than 1 are found
in the pre- and postweights, then the question is:
Is the Petri
net then bounded?
Does it have
a finite reachability graph?
If not, then it
is not 1-safe either.
And if it has a finite reachability
graph, then you can look at it
and see if the constant you can
choose to bound it is even 1.
Which would not have been
the case in this example.
Now we have seen
examples for different constellations.
We have seen bounded
but not 1-safe Petri nets.
Namely, what
is just here.
And we have seen
some 1-safe Petri nets.
What we haven't seen yet, which I
will discuss in a video, would be
an example of
an unbounded Petri net.